<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
<title>Libstk - The Set-top Box Toolkit</title>
<bookinfo> 
	<author><firstname>Marc</firstname><surname>Strämke</surname></author>
	<author><firstname>Darren</firstname><surname>Hart</surname></author>
	<title>Libstk - The Set-top Box Toolkit</title>
	<pubdate>25 March 2003</pubdate>
	<corpauthor>Libstk-Team</corpauthor>
</bookinfo>
<chapter>
	<title>Internals</title>
	<section>
		<title>Widget Tree</title>
		<para>	
			The single most important part of the library is the widget tree structure.
		</para>
		<para>
			The root of the Tree is the Application Object (stk::application), it contains a list of state which all represents
			one set of visible widgets at a time, these are contained in the children list of all containers.(state is a container too)</para>
		<para>
			All linking in the widget tree is established by using smart pointers, Parents use shared_ptrs to link to their children, which expresses
			an ownership of the childrens. Children use weak_ptrs to establish a link to their parents, this is used instead of a shared_ptr because
			a child doesnt/cannot own his own parent in terms of reference counting.
		</para>
		<para>
			<figure>
				<title>Example of the Widget tree</title>
				<mediaobject><imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/widget_tree_example.png"  />
				</imageobject></mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Event handling</title>
			<para>To be written(Describe dispatching of events with the widget tree)</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Drawing</title>
			<para>
				Something happens to a widget that causes it to need to be redrawn.  It calls parent_->redraw(rect_), the parent (which is a container) adds the rect to its redraw_rect_ (rectangle + rectangle uses the min and max points to form a new rectangle), and calls parent_->redraw(redraw_rect_) and so on until application is reached.  The next time application starts to draw it calls current_state_->draw().  The state only draws the portion defined by redraw_rect_ (this speeds up redraw time and ensures the background for potentially partially transparent widgets or fonts is drawn), it then calls draw on all its children widgets who intersect the redraw_rect.  Containers only draw the area defined by redraw_rect_, leaf widgets always redraw themselves entirely. 
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Fonts</title>
		<para>
			Fonts in Libstk are drawn using the Freetype2 Rendering engine, in this engine
			rendering glyphs is quite expensive, to counter this we are employing a cached glyph system in which
			we cache the rendered glyphs for one single font and font property set in system memory.
		</para>
		<para>
			For caching there are multiple layers involved. The lowest layer is the <classname>font</classname> class, this class
			is responsible for Driving the rendering engine, and caching single glyph images. Each instance of the font class is constructed
			with a set of properties describing all aspects of font rendering, font size, the font name and attributes. (outline only, italic or bold)		
		</para>
		<para>
			The next higher layer is the font manager, this is a singleton object which  manages <emphasis>all</emphasis> instances of
			the font class, this is done to avoid creating font objects with the same properties multiple times, which would duplicate
			the caching effort in multiple places and waste memory. The user interacts with the singleton by calling a single function 
			called get_font which takes a font property set as its sole argument and returns a shared_ptr to the right font class instances
			with the corresponding property set, it is very important that the user stores this shared_ptr as long as he is using this set
			of font properties to draw text, when the returned shared_ptr is destroyed (goes out of scope) the associated font objects
			<emphasis>will</emphasis> be destroyed except when there are multiple users of the same object.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Drawing</title>
		<para>To be written (Should describe surface class et al)</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
<appendix>
	<title>Coding Standards</title>
	<section>	
		<title>Naming</title>
		<para>
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Variable Names</title>
			<para>
				Variable Names should be descriptive,short and concise, different words have to be seperated by a underscore.
			</para>		
			<formalpara>
				<title>Examples of <emphasis>Good</emphasis> style</title>
				<para>temp_widget, temporary_widget, big_button .. </para>
			</formalpara>
			<formalpara>
				<title>Examples of <emphasis>Bad</emphasis> style</title>
				<para>TempWidget,tw,tWidget,wtTemp...</para>
			</formalpara>
			<para>
				Variables in Class scope should have an underscore as their suffix and never be global, global Variables should only be provided by
				property accessor-methods.
			</para> 
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Properties</title>
		<para>
			Properties which are contained in the public API of any Library object should 
			<emphasis>only</emphasis> be accesible trough Accessor Methods.
		</para>
		<para>
			The Property Accessor methods should have the following prototype (T is the Propertie's value, property the propertie's name)
		</para>
		<para>Get: T property() const;</para>
		<para>Set: void property(T);</para>
		<para>
			The get Method as shown by the const specification should not have any Side effects on the classes' state. (FIXME:HAVE TO DISCUSS THIS)
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>	
		<title>Formatting</title>
		<section>
			<title>Identation</title>
			<para>
				Code should be Indented according to the Ansi Style, Look at the Artistic Style Documentation for a full specifcation of this(astyle.sf.net,FIXME).
				Code can be automaticly formatted with the <emphasis>astyle --style=ansi</emphasis> command.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Spacing</title>
			<para>
				Operators should be seperated by spaces. 
			</para>
			<para>
				Good: a = b + 1; 
			</para>
			<para>
				Bad: a=b+1;
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Common Practises</title>
		<para>There are some Common practises in the Libstk library that should be followed by contributors.</para>
		<para>Every class should have 2 typedefs defined. classname::ptr as a boost::shared_ptr&lt;classname&gt; 
			and classname::weak_ptr as a boost::weak_ptr&lt;classname&gt;. This makes it possible to easily define smart pointers to
			libstk Objects without polluting the global namespace with type definitions.</para>
	</section>
</appendix>
</book>
